This entire process of embryonic folding not only
organizes the placement of my joints,
but it also begins to induce a phase of delimitation of the embryo.
A set of four embryonic structures.
There are four embryonic structures.
These four structures are the transverse septum, the
pleural membranes,
peritoneal, the
paraxial mesoderm of the
truncal wall, and the
esophageal mesenchyme.
Beyond the
prechordal plate, in the
cephalic region, the mesenchymal
cells of the embryonic disc
will become the pericardium
and the transverse septum.
That's the notochord.
Paracordal means
next to.
Precordal,
means there and beyond the precordal plate, that is to say here, in
the cephalic area, the mesenchymal cells, the
mesenchymal cells from the
embryonic disc, will become
the pericardium and the transverse septum.
In other words,
Not only is your heart already developing above your head,
but how can we explain that?
By the fact that it's doing that movement.
That means they are already in place, actually.
They are already there.
And that's very important because it's something that,
in classical embryology, we don't see.
We describe the movement of the heart, you see?
It descends, but no it doesn't descend, it's the other one that rises, you see?
?
The same goes for the kidneys, we describe the ascent of the joint, but no, the kidney stays
in place, it's the rest that descends.
When I have this phrase it immediately clicks for me, it means that the pericardium and
your diaphragm are a functional unit,
and we will see that when we study the heart, we will observe that the rhythmicity
of the heart is supported by the pericardial fascia. In other words, if I remove
the electricity alone
from the heart, it is not enough to sustain it and there is a closed oscillating system,
almost like
a rather brilliant energy, which is generated in the pericardium to support the
heart in its rhythmicity.
And in addition, it is completely connected between the heart
and the diaphragm.
These are not two separate things; they initially arise from almost the same cells that will organize.
We see that it ends up up there, and then it does this, it’s how they are integrated here,
both at the level of the pericardium which is here, and
the transverse septum which is there.
So the folding, the notochord induces a specific
movement at the level of my neural tube which in turn leads to a
neural groove movement that organizes the
lateral structure into a small vessel that becomes a
nutritional supply but a brake for relative growth by the very important development
of my neural tube.
The electroderm around it wraps up and in this wrapping movement,
we can already imagine that the cells are there, you see, here.
Well, they come to do this, so it doesn't move, it does that.
And that's how these mesenchymal cells integrate
to form the future pericardial tissue and create the diaphragmatic bud.
It brings cells that will develop around.
All of this grows and at some point, my vesicle...
The vitelline pedicle stops growing. It has finished its job.
It's just a small remnant that gets inserted with vitelline vessels
around what we call the umbilical reason with the umbilical networks.
The vesicle will be integrated into the pedicle to form the umbilical cord
and the pericardium will integrate with the transverse septum to form this tissue
whose origin is initially beyond the precordal plate.
Here we can see the transverse septum, you see, which is here, which
is an important tissue.
We will see that there is growth.
Initially, the transverse septum is here, you see, at the fourth
week.
Then at the fifth week, it horizontalizes, you
see, and then it starts to descend, here, like this.
But actually, look, it comes here, and then it goes down completely.
Like this. So what does that mean? Initially, it has its origin
when it is
2 mm, it originates at the level of the very high cervical area. C3,
C4, which is the origin
of the phrenic nerve. And then it
ultimately finds itself in the lumbar region,
bringing it here. What does this drawing mean in
biodynamics?
It's wrong. Why?
Because it goes down while it’s...
The rest comes up. Exactly. That's the image of the
train leaving. I think I'm moving, but in fact, I haven't moved.
The truth is that this becomes a point of support
and everything else around it moves.
Do you understand the idea?
So the diaphragm sets itself, positions itself, and I have huge growth
around,
and it’s this growth of the posterior part, you see here, 1, and then
the growth, 2, the embryo is actually growing, you see,
and it creates a, in fact, it will even create an absorption space here, as
it grows, it will create a space here, you see, between here, and now I have a space
that opens up here.
And what will be attracted there, into this space?
My lungs, which are a suction field as we will discuss,
which will be sucked here, here, which we will see in phase 2, at the
viscerocranium.
The diaphragmatic origin is found very, very high,
at the level of the second and third cervical vertebrae.
But it’s all the part above
that grows. So the nerve
is not pulled like this,
but is almost pulled like this.
We see this setup
of this diaphragm
linked with
this excessive growth
that we will see, which we will study tomorrow
in detail, why the embryo
at some point, stops
in its flexion.
The embryo straightens up. Why
does it straighten? What happens?
It’s a question of fluids on the sclera.
with the straightening of the telencephalon.
The ascent of my neural tube and the descent of my digestive system.
That’s what will create this space here, the integration.
Here we can clearly see in a section the different tissues, transverse septum,
the pleuro-peritoneal membranes and also what is called the meso
esophageal
and the para-axial membranes that are there.
Not only is working on a diaphragm about working on all these spaces
here.
Often, we work on them here.
But in fact, working on a diaphragm not only means releasing all this,
these lateral spaces, but also the aorta, the
vena cava, and the esophagus,
and especially the esophageal junction.
Because it is a very important area for clearing a diaphragm.
Many patients suffer from...
esophagitis, digestive troubles
at the level of the esophagus, a lot.
Well, that blocks your diaphragm.
It is essential to release and clear
this periesophageal space
with the Trest muscle,
the Lancsouver muscle,
this little periesophageal space
that can block the entire digestive system
that is suspended in relation to the carotid foramina,
in relation to the prejugular system,
in relation to...
your anterior and posterior pterygoid attachments,
at the base of the skull's lower part,
which can create here everything, it is supported.
And so if you don't have the bell ringing in your head
when it descends here,
you are not free on your symphysis.
Because actually, what happens here?
You have a magical continuity,
with a small muscle which is a muscle
that I consider to be the magician of the system...
of sphincter openings,
of organizing the whole
functional integrity
of your primitive vegetative system
and even current
in relation to that.
And what is it called? It continues here.
Look, it does this
and it continues there. What do we call that?
The Tret muscle.
Which contains two types of fibers. Muscle fibers
and non-muscle fibers.
So two types of different information.
This is a muscle that can open
or close the sphincters.
The falciform ligament, the greater omentum
are derived elements
from the transverse septum,
so what can we say?
That 1. I have a continuity
not only from my mesenchymal cells
via the pericardial system
and the transverse septum
but also
from the transverse septum will derive
a part of my falciform ligament, and at the same time
the greater omentum, which are elements
that are derived from this transverse septum.
And I remind you that the greater omentum
is part of this
functional integrity of the
diaphragm. I am here,
I have the Winslow hiatus, and I pass
behind the retro-gastric sac.
You see? So I go up
toward the area of the
bronchus, I orient my left bronchus,
I go toward the spleen, and then I descend,
I pass over the
colon,
and I descend to form
a coalescence of four layers
to form the greater omentum.
Lymphatic messenger,
B, T and M, motility,
in relation, all of this,
with my diaphragmatic system.
Another important thing,
is this relationship, you see,
with what we call the curvilinear ligaments.
You know this, they are here, you see.
This is the curvilinear ligament,
the arcuate ligament,
with the psoas arcade,
the median arcuate ligament
with the aortic hiatus.
And above, you have an important passage,
this continuity with the Tret ligament.
But this is interesting
because this is an arcuate ligament
with the quadratus lumborum.
The median arcuate ligament
with the psoas arcade.
This means that the diaphragm
continues indirectly
through my common masses,
through my quadratus lumborum up to here,
and even up to here in relation to my psoas.
They are in direct relation with my diaphragm.
This is a fascial continuity
of diaphragmatic organization.
And how can esophagitis disrupt
even a movement of the knee, for instance,
by disrupting your mechanics?
Each diaphragm
should be considered in relation to the other diaphragms.
Each of the three major diaphragms, cervical, thoracic,
pelvic,
an imbalance in one disrupts the others. Furthermore, I find myself in a negative pressure
with a positive pressure.
That is to say, it is a pressure regulator, so it is a regulator of
tension, thus it is a hydraulic and even thermal regulator.
You see how this digestive diaphragm, vascular,
lymphatic, is a lymphatic pump?
How all this relates to its system, with the
esophagus, with the entire system,
cardiac, with its heart relation, and all its relationship with the phohepatis, and
all its relationship
posteriorly with the greater omentum. And behind, we will find all the
relationship with the quadratus lumborum,
and moreover with the psoas. But
all of that is a single continuity from the heart, from the esophagus,
from the base of the skull, therefore from the cranium-sacral axis.
Whether it’s the purely notochordal axis or the purely
Corrings axis.
The costodiaphragmatic recesses are sacs for the accumulation of exudates, waste,
both from
transpulmonary and transperitoneal exudates.
What does this phrase mean?
I develop bronchitis, I cough, I get some swelling, I
have little microbes.
I need to eliminate these microbes, or they won’t remain complicated.
They must be eliminated.
They pass.
That’s why very often,
when you develop pneumonia afterwards,
you have blocked pulmonary bases.
It’s the same thing
if you have gastric issues.
If you do something like that, you’re going to eliminate.
It builds up.
They need one main thing,
it's...
space.
This is where we see that the human body
is a unit on the cellular level, 1, on the tissue level,
2, and these reactions
of defense and integration can occur on any level.
Why? Because
there is a tissue continuity of the splanchnopleura and of the somatopleura. That
is
what we just saw with the diaphragm.